Finding Aid for the Knox Mellon California Democratic Council Papers LSC.1061
UCLA Library Special Collections
Knox Mellon California Democratic Council Papers
1957-1969
UCLA Library Special Collections
Mellon, Knox
LSC.1061
7.5 Linear Feet
William Knox Mellon, Jr. was a professor of history at Immaculate Heart College and the Democratic nominee for the CA 24th District for Congress in 1962. Mellon became treasurer of the Oral History Association. Collection consists of correspondence, records, and printed material relating to the California Democratic Council and to CA politics in general during the 1960s.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Knox Mellon, Jr., 1968.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942334043606533
Biography
William Knox Mellon, Jr. was born on Oct. 20, 1925 in Houston, TX; BA, Pomona College, 1950; MA, Claremont College, 1953; Ph.D, Claremont Graduate School, 1972; became a professor of history at Immaculate Heart College; Democratic nominee for the CA 24th District for Congress, 1962; became treasurer, Oral History Assn.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, records, and printed material relating to the California Democratic Council and to CA politics in general during the 1960s. Includes clippings, newsletters, pamphlets, and periodicals, files on Democratic candidates, and CDC by-laws, files on conventions, committees, board meetings, and the 1960 presidential campaign.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Political files covering local politics and candidates (boxes 1-4)
Miscellaneous subject files (boxes 5-8)
Newsletters, commentaries, pamphlets by and about the CDC (boxes 9-10)
California Democratic Council files, 1959-1967 (boxes 11-15).
Related Material
Joyce Fadem Papers (Collection 1109). Available at the Library Special Collections.
California Democratic Council Records (Collection 1389). Available at the Library Special Collections.
Charles G. Gant California Democratic Council Records (Collection 1073). Available at the Library Special Collections.
Joseph L. Wyatt Collection of California Democratic Council Records (Collection 1082). Available at the Library Special Collections.
History teachers -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; California Democratic Council; Mellon, Knox -- Archives
- Political files
  - A - CH
    - Bennett, William., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Democratic candidate for attorney general, 1966.
    - Brown, George E. Jr., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Assemblyman. Re: 1962 Congressional race. (c.f. box 9)
    - Brown, Pat, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Governor. Political literature, etc. 1959-1963.
    - By-laws of CDC clubs - 49th and 54th assembly districts., undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1960 campaign and election (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1962 campaign - political literature (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1963 legislative session (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1964 campaign - political literature (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - CL-CZ
    - Claremont - Democratic Club, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Claremont - Democratic Club, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Claremont - Democratic Club, d - dots., 1958-1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Scattered issues.
    - Claremont - Democratic Club - Programs, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Claremont - Democratic Club - Programs, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Claremont politics, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Congressional districts - 24th, 1962-1964 (Box 2)
      - Candidate committees, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Endorsing convention, 1962 March (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Newsletter, 1963 November - 1964 April (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Congressional districts - 25th, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Miscellaneous printed material.
  - D-L
    - Democratic candidates' campaign conference, Washington, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Democratic State Central Committee (California), 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Egly, Paul, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Democratic candidate for assembly in 49th district, 1960. (includes campaign literature for Republican opponent, Houston Flourney.)
    - Faull, Harry, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Democratic candidate for assembly in 49th district, 1960. Clippings re: Congressman George Kasem's support of Faull.
    - 49th Assembly district democratic council, 1957-1966 (Box 3)
      - 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - 1960-1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence of corresponding secretary (Cricket Levering), undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Gelber, Milton, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Democratic candidate for assembly in 49th District, 1962. (includes campaign literature for Republican incumbent, Houston Flourney.)
    - Kasem, George, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Includes correspondence, clippings, campaign literature.
    - Los Angeles County Democratic Central Committee (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - M-Z
    - Maps (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Mellon, Knox, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
      Democratic candidate for Congress, 24th district, 1962. (Includes campaign literature for Republican incumbent, Glen Libscomb.)
    - Membership lists (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous campaigns and candidates supported by CDC (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Mosk, Stanley, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      re: 1958 campaign for State attorney general.
    - Nevins, Richard, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Campaign literature for Board of Equalization, 4th district, 1958.
    - O'Connell, John, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Democratic candidate for U.S. Senate, 1962.
    - Roybal, Edward R., 1962 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Voter registration (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Weinberger, Martin, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Democratic candidate for assembly in 49th district, 1958.
    - Yorty, Samuel William, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Mayorality campaign, 1961.
- Subject files
  - A-C
    - Academic freedom (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Africa (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Agriculture (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - American character (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) (Box 5, Folder 5)
      General note
      (c.f. box 9)
    - Automation (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Berlin (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Budget, U.S. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Buffums (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Capital punishment (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - China (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Civil defense (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Civil defense - clippings (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Civil rights (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Consumer Council (clippings) (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Council for a Livable World (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Cuba (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - D-O
    - Disarmament (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Education (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight David (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Fair employment practices commission (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Farm newsletter - Senator Hubert H. Humphrey (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Federal communications commission (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - France (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Handwriting analysis (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - House Un-American activities committee (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Human rights (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - India (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Jews in Germany (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - John Birch society (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Labor (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Migrant workers (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Narcotics (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - New Party - Canada (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Nixon, Richard M. (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Operation Abolition (film) clippings, reviews, etc. (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - P-Z
    - Peace corps (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Peace groups (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Planning (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Platform for Peace (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Population (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Poverty (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Race relations (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Regulatory agencies (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Russia (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Southern Conference Educational Fund (Box 7, Folder 10)
      (c.f. box 9 for Southern Patriot)
    - U.N. Bonds (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Viet Nam (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Water (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Water - Mexicali (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - World Federalist (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Pamphlets, clippings, correspondence, etc
  Re: health and medical care in California.
  - California Democratic Council. 3rd annual issues conference program, "Medical care and the public interest." (Box 8)
  - Family expenditure patterns for personal health services, and nationwide surveys. Health information series 14., 1953 1958 (Box 8)
  - Health insurance benefits for personal health services. Health information series 15. (Box 8)
  - Medical care among those aged 65 and over. Health information series 16., 1960 (Box 8)
  - Meeting medical care costs among the aging. Health information series 17., 1960 (Box 8)
  - Colorado's medical care program for the aged. HIF Perspectives., 1960 (Box 8)
  - Harpers Magazine, 1960 July, October (Box 8)
  - Claremont Courier, 1961 February 16 and 23 (Box 8)
  - Policy statement on medical care approved by CDC convention, 1961 March 5 (Box 8)
- Newsletters, commentaries, etc.
  - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU)
    - Civil liberties, 1963 November - 1964 October (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Open forum, 1963 July - 1964 January (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Brown, George Congressman, 1963 June - 1964 July (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Reports from Washington (6 issues).
    - Democratic volunteers committee of California, ca. 1964 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Friends committee on legislation, 1958 March - 1962 March (Box 9, Folder 4)
      FCL Action.
    - Friends committee on National legislation Washington newsletter, 1963 August - 1965 August (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Fair employment practices commission, 1963 May - 1964 October (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Fair practices news.
    - National committee for an effective Congress, 1961 July - 1965 April; (4 issues) (Box 9, Folder 7)
      Congressional report.
    - SANE World, 1963 September - 1964 November (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Southern conference education fun, 1962 February - 1965 January (Box 9, Folder 9)
      The southern patriot.
    - Windmiller, Marshall, 1961 August - 1963 December (Box 9, Folder 10)
      The Commentary of Marshall Windmiller.
    - Winter, William, 1963 September - 1964 October (Box 9, Folder 11)
      William Winter comments...
  - Pamphlets and publications of and about the CDC (Box 10)
    Includes programs and statements for 1963 CDC Issues Conference, also scattered issues of some periodicals.
- CDC files, 1959-1967
  - CDC Board meetings, 1960-1967
    - Los Angeles, 1960 June (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - San Francisco, 1960 August (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Bakersfield, 1960 November (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Sacramento, 1961 January (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Fresno, 1961 April (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Fresno, 1961 June (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - San Francisco, 1961 August (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Santa Monica, 1961 October (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Fresno, 1961 December (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Yosemite, 1962 February (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Fresno, 1962 April (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Long Beach, 1962 June (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Asilomar, 1962 August (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Santa Barbara, 1962 October (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Fresno, 1962 December (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Bakersfield, 1963 January (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Sacramento, 1963 May (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Santa Monica, 1963 June (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Fresno, 1963 September (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Fresno, 1963 November (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Los Angeles, 1965 October (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Bakersfield, 1965 April (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Fresno, 1965 November (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - San Francisco, 1966 April (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Santa Monica, 1966 September (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Lake Tahoe, 1966 November (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - Fresno, 1967 February (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - San Mateo, 1967 April (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - Coronada, 1967 June (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - Long Beach, 1967 September (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - San Jose, 1967 November (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - CDC By-laws, 1963-1964 (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - CDC Files, 1959-1962
    - Democratic club programs, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - CDC conventions, 1957 and 1959 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - CDC convention and issues conference, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Legislature - Sample ideas, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - CDC issues program, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - CDC convention, 1960 February (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - CDC journal, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Committees, etc., 1960 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - CDC convention, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - 25th congressional district's delegation and caucus, convention, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - CDC journal, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - CDC issues conference (medical care), 1961 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Issues conference, region II, 1961 November (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Issues resource material, 1961-1962 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Legislative seminar, Sacramento, 1961 January (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Role of CDC, 1961-1962 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Campaign - 1962 election (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - CDC committee structure, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - CDC convention, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - CDC Files, 1963-1965
    - Issues for 1963 CDC convention (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Issues conference, region II, 1963 March (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Issues - 24th congressional district, 1963 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Election reform conference, 1963 March (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - CDC convention, Bakersfield, 1963 March (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - 5 man program planning committee, 1963 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Assembly bill 2922 ("truth in endorsements") and Jesse Unruh (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - CDC convention, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Issues - Program planning committee, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - CDC convention, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - CDC Files and Miscellaneous Files, 1966-1967
    - CDC convention, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Credentials, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - CDC convention, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - CDC Directors reports, 1960-1964 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Legislative action committee - Correspondence with California legislators, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      RE: Fisher bill on teacher requirements, 1961. Includes letters from Houston Flournoy, Augustus Hawkins, Hugo Fisher, and U.S. Senators Clair Engle and Thomas Kuchel.
    - L.A.C. - Assembly Interim committees, 1961 June - 1967 January (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Los Angeles County Council of CDC, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - CDC - Miscellaneous correspondence, etc., ca. 1961-1964 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - CDC - Miscellaneous printed items, clippings, etc., 1962-1966 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - CDC Historical File
    [emphasizes 1960 presidential campaign]
    - Caucus for Brown delegation, 1960 February (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Convention tickets, 1960 June (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Mailing for primary, 1960 July (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - National convention, 1960 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - 1960 presidential campaign (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Party (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Scrapbook - clippings, etc. (Box 15, Folder 7-8)